Orwell S. Chaffee Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Orwell S. Chaffee Papers
1846-1854, 1903
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Chaffee, Orwell S.
.25 linear feet
Orwell S. Chaffee (1807-1887) was a silk manufacturer in the Mansfield/Willimantic area of eastern Connecticut. Son-in-law to Joseph Conant, he worked in, and later managed, Conant's silk mill until 1838 when he purchased property in Chaffeeville and established his own silk mill. The collection contains correspondence, receipts and invoices addressed to Mr. O.S. Chaffee.
MSS19980138
Biography
Orwell S. Chaffee was the son of Frederick Chaffee, a prosperous farmer who resided in northeast Mansfield, Connecticut, and Katherine Knowlton Chaffee. Orwell was born 10 June 1807 in Ashford, Connecticut and moved with his parents to Mansfield as a boy. Upon his marriage to Lucinda Amelia Conant, daughter of Joseph Conant, Orwell began his career in the silk manufacturing industry working in his father-in-law's mill. After Mr. Conant's retirement from the business, Orwell Chaffee continued to manage the business until about 1838, when he purchased a factory site in what is now the Chaffeeville area of Mansfield.
Mr. Chaffee tore down the existing building and erected a larger structure, a dam and commenced production of silk thread and braid. In later years, his son, J. Dwight Chaffee, became a partner and in 1872 they established a factory in Willimantic, Connecticut under the title of O.S. Chaffee & Son.
Mr. Chaffee was active in the business until his death on 2 April 1887. Mr. Chaffee is buried in the Gurleyville Cemetery in Mansfield, Connecticut.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, receipts, bills and invoices addressed to Mr. Chaffee concerning both his personal and professional life.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type and chronologically therein.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business. See especially, H.K.H. Silk Company Records and Cheney Brothers Silk Manufacturing Company Records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Chaffee, Orwell S.
Family Names:
Chaffee.; Conant.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Financial Records.
Occupations:
Manufacturer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Detailed Description
- Papers, 1846-1854, 1903
  - Biographical Record, 1903 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1846 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1847 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1848 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1850 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1851 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1852 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1853 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1854 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Receipts and Bills, 1847-1854 (Box 1:, Folder 10)